<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Dokku | Mirco Zeiss]]></title>
  <link href="http://mircozeiss.com/categories/dokku/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mircozeiss.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-11T21:04:54+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://mircozeiss.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mirco Zeiss]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dokku in-depth tutorial - Your private PaaS on Amazon EC2]]></title>
    <link href="http://mircozeiss.com/dokku-in-depth-tutorial-your-private-saas-on-amazon-ec2/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-10T22:20:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mircozeiss.com/dokku-in-depth-tutorial-your-private-saas-on-amazon-ec2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you want complete control over your servers and at the same time the simplicity to deploy as easy as
<code>git push server master</code> <a href="https://github.com/progrium/dokku">Dokku</a> will be your next favorite tool.</p>

<p>In this post I will walk you through the process of installing Dokku on a fresh Amazon EC2 instance running Ubuntu Server
13.04.</p>

<h3>Set up your Amazon EC2 instance</h3>

<p>Log in to your AWS console and go to EC2. From your dashboard click on "Launch Instance". Under step one "Choose AMI" find
"Ubuntu Server 13.04" and click on "Select".</p>

<p><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/mircozeiss.com/dokku/01_choose_ami.png" title="Ubuntu Server 13.04 instance" ></p>

<p>In step two "Choose Instance Type" select the micro instance. It has enough power for any small prototype and is eligible
for the AWS free usage tier. If you need more RAM, disk space or CPU you can also select one of the other instances. For
this post it doesn't matter, as the following steps will be the same.</p>

<p><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/mircozeiss.com/dokku/02_choose_instance_type.png" title="Choose Instance Type" ></p>

<p>In step three "Configure Instance" I left everything as is.</p>

<p><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/mircozeiss.com/dokku/03_configure_instance.png" title="Configure Instance" ></p>

<p>The same goes for step four "Add storage". Usually you don't need a lot of storage. For images, videos and other
files I always use S3.</p>

<p><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/mircozeiss.com/dokku/04_add_storage.png" title="Add Storage" ></p>

<p>In step five "Tag Instance" give your instance a name. That makes it easier later on to find it in the list of all
your instances. I chose "Node.js via Dokku".</p>

<p><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/mircozeiss.com/dokku/05_tag_instance.png" title="Tag Instance" ></p>

<p>Leave everything as is in step six "Configure Security Group". The wizard will create a new security group for your
instance. In my case it is called "launch-wizard-1". At the bottom you can see that only port 22 is open for SSH access.
We will change this later on to access our instance through the web with a browser.</p>

<p><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/mircozeiss.com/dokku/06_configure_security_group.png" title="Configure Security Group" ></p>

<p>Last but not least check that everything is correct in step seven "Review". Click on "Launch" to start your fresh instance.</p>

<p><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/mircozeiss.com/dokku/07_review.png" title="Review" ></p>

<p>To connect to this instance via SSH you need to create a key pair (or use an existing one if you have). I named mine
"dokku" and downloaded the "dokku.pem" file.</p>

<p><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/mircozeiss.com/dokku/08_key_pair.png" title="Key Pair" ></p>

<p>Et voilà you've created a new instance, downloaded the necessary key pair and after a short amount of time
you'll see the instance within your list of instances with a green status indicator that says "running". That concludes
the first section and in the next one we will connect to the instance and install Dokku.</p>

<p><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/mircozeiss.com/dokku/10_instance_screenshot.png" title="Instance Screenshot" ></p>

<h3>Install Dokku</h3>

<p>First of all connect to your server via SSH. I'll simply use the terminal but you can use any tool you want. Select
the "Node.js via Dokku" instance from the list and on top of the page click on "Connect". A popup window will open
with further instructions.</p>

<p><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/mircozeiss.com/dokku/11_connect_to_instance.png" title="Connect To Your Instance" ></p>

<p>At the top "A standalone SSH client" should be selected. Open your terminal and change the working directory to the folder
where you put the previously downloaded "docker.pem" file. Then run <code>chmod 400 dokku.pem</code> to change the permissions for your
key pair. Afterwards copy the line under "Example" and paste it into your terminal. Don't worry about the message that the
authenticity cannot be established. Simply answer the prompt with "yes" and press enter.</p>

<p><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/mircozeiss.com/dokku/12_RSA_fingerprint.png" title="RSA fingerprint" ></p>

<p>Afterwards you should see a welcome message from your Ubuntu server.</p>

<p><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/mircozeiss.com/dokku/13_connected_to_server.png" title="Server success message" ></p>

<p>Now that you are connected to your server we can install Dokku. Follow the instructions from the <a href="https://github.com/progrium/dokku#installing">GitHub page</a>.
Run <code>wget -qO- https://raw.github.com/progrium/dokku/master/bootstrap.sh | sudo bash</code>. That will install all the necessary tools needed to run Dokku.
The whole process will take about five minutes and at the end you will see a message that asks you to copy
your public key to the server.</p>

<p><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/mircozeiss.com/dokku/14_dokku_installed.png" title="Dokku installed" ></p>

<p>Make sure you replace <code>root@ip-10-228-95-82</code> with the username and address you've used before to connect to your server.
Then you have to run <code>gitreceive upload-key progrium</code> as an admin with <code>sudo</code>. It doesn't say it in the success message
but on GitHub under <a href="https://github.com/progrium/dokku#configuring">Configuring</a> it is stated. Finally you can replace
<code>progrium</code> with any username you want. It will be the username that is used by git. I simply chose <code>dokku</code>.</p>

<p><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/mircozeiss.com/dokku/15_copy_ssh_key.png" title="Copy SSH Key" ></p>

<p>The last step to make Dokku work is to create a <code>VHOST</code> file in <code>/home/git/</code>. On your server change the directory to <code>/home/git/</code>
and run <code>sudo touch VHOST</code> to create the file and <code>sudo nano VHOST</code> to open the file with the nano editor. Then paste
the public DNS of your instance into this file and close it with CTRL+X. Afterwards run <code>cat VHOST</code> to make sure the
DNS was saved correctly.</p>

<p><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/mircozeiss.com/dokku/17_setting_vhost.png" title="Setting VHOST" ></p>

<p>That's it! Your server is ready, Dokku is ready and the only thing left is our app.</p>

<h3>Node.js app</h3>

<p>We will simply use the <a href="http://expressjs.com/">Express</a> starter app and run it on our server. In a terminal on your local
computer run <code>express</code> and <code>npm install</code> to create the app. As Dokku is inspired by <a href="https://www.heroku.com/">Heroku</a> every app
needs a Procfile to tell our server which commands it should run to start our express app. Usually we run <code>node app.js</code> to start
our app and therefore we have to write the same into the Procfile. Run <code>touch Procfile</code> to create it,
<code>echo web: node app.js &gt; Procfile</code> to put the right command into the file and <code>cat Procfile</code> to verify that everything
worked as expected.</p>

<p><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/mircozeiss.com/dokku/19_procfile.png" title="Procfile" ></p>

<p>It is also recommended to create a <code>.gitignore</code> file and to put the <code>node_modules/</code> directory inside. We don't have
to copy this folder to our server as Dokku will run <code>npm install</code> which will install all required modules from our <code>package.json</code>.
Run <code>touch .gitignore</code> and <code>echo node_modules/ &gt; .gitignore</code> to set up this file.</p>

<p><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/mircozeiss.com/dokku/16_gitignore.png" title="Gitignore" ></p>

<p>Now you are ready to deploy. Initialize git with <code>git init</code>, add all the files with <code>git add .</code> and write your first
commit message <code>git commit -m "init"</code>. To deploy the code to our server we have to set the remote target for git. Run
<code>git remote add [name] git@[DNS]:[appname]</code> to add our remote server. For <code>[name]</code> I chose <code>aws</code>, for <code>[DNS]</code> I copied
my public DNS from the Amazon EC2 dashboard and as <code>[appname]</code> I selected <code>node-js-example</code>.</p>

<p><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/mircozeiss.com/dokku/18_git_add_remote.png" title="Git Add Remote" ></p>

<p>Now simply run <code>git push aws master</code> to deploy the app to our server. You will see a success message that says that our app
is available under some subdomain. Unfortunately that doesn't work and we have to access it via the public DNS and its
public port.</p>

<p>To see the port of our app connect to the server via SSH and run <code>sudo docker ps</code>. You should see one running process
and at the very right you'll see the public port of our app.</p>

<p><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/mircozeiss.com/dokku/20_sudo_docker_ps.png" title="Sudo Docker PS" ></p>

<p>You might remember from the beginning where we talked about the security groups and how we will get back to this topic later
on. Well that moment is now. In order to access the instance from the web you'll have to open the port the app is running on.
In the AWS console click on "Security Groups" on the left side and select the one we used for our instance. In my case it
was "launch-wizard-1". At the bottom click on "Inbound" and enter your port in "Port range". For me it was port 49153. Click
on "Add Rule" and "Apply Rule Changes" to save the settings.</p>

<p>Now copy the public DNS of your server and afterwards the port of your app to the browser's address bar and see the Express app
running. Yeah!</p>

<p><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/mircozeiss.com/dokku/22_express_app_running_on_aws_ec2_instance.png" title="Express app running on AWS EC2 instance" ></p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>We now have a server running our app in an isolated Docker image. Through SSH we have complete control over the app
and we can install any additional packages we want. Using Docker we can easily create more apps on the same server without
interfering with running processes. At the same time we are able to deploy new code as easy as <code>git push aws master</code>
and see the changes live within a short amount of time. Dokku and Docker are under heavy development but it's definetely worth
to check them out. They really make live easier. Big thumbs up for the creators and the community helping with the
development.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
